this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello this is marcus
Blankenship for software engineering
radio today I have with me Brian helm
aghh brian is the CTO and co-founder of
zapier a workflow automation tool used
by over 2 million people to connect the
work apps that they use every day prior
to zapier brian worked in product
development for veterans United Home
Loans
he's an alumni of University of Missouri
at Columbia I'll be talking with Brian
today about managing distributed
engineering teams Brian welcome to
software engineering radio thank you I'm
excited to be here Marcus I'm excited
for this too I also want to disclose
that I'm currently a zapier customer and
in the past have applied for positions
at that company so let's begin with this
what is a distributed team Brian so a
distributed team is exactly like it
sounds especially if you think of
distributed systems you think of any of
that stuff it's where you don't have
your entire team co-located in one place
everyone is really working from their
own office their own space their own
area there's a lot of really cool stuff
about that means you get to work with
people all over the world they're all
really talented folks you're not bound
by some geographic area there's lots of
quat you know quality of life things
that are great about it as well
there's no commute there's a lot of
really cool things like that but in a
nutshell it means that you interact with
people through work and much like we are
over audio calls or VoIP calls or you
work with tools like slack or github to
do all your work and there's no central
office certainly for us we're 100%
remote 100% distributed so there is no
office some places they kind of have a
mix you'll see that every now and then
but yeah distribute it just means no no
central office where everybody
right yeah that's really interesting
I've heard other people tell me that
they were distributed and what they
meant was that their development team
was distributed across four offices in
the United States or London Texas New
York California that's what they meant
by distributed but you have no
colocation at all yeah that's right and
I think there's probably a distinction
because sometimes these these terms sort
of are interchangeable and used for
different stuff so for us we say remote
we're a hundred percent remote and to us
that really signifies that every single
person works remotely there is no you
know like Denver office in like Bay Area
office a New York office which is
commonly I think the the other term or
the other definition of the term like
distributed that people we have
distributed offices so that I think is
like the key distinction for what we
would say yeah a hundred percent remote
versus distributed offices or other
permutations within that I mean they're
all kind of on the spectrum I suppose
but for us we're all the way down the
line to 100% remote no office everyone
works from their own place and we've
been that way since the beginning I've
hear a lot of people talking that remote
teams are harder to manage than
co-located teams where the manager can
walk around and see what's happening do
you think this is true I don't I don't
think so I've worked in both
environments and I'll say humans are
humans in both environments so some of
that I'll say for sure the challenges
that you'll hit and scaling a company
you might hit a little bit sooner as
distributed fully distributed fully
remote company and I would say a great
example and certainly for zapier is how
we communicate was something we had to
codify and lock in a lot earlier then
probably co-located companies can kind
of get away with you have kind of have
everybody together and like they can tap
each other on the shoulder and you can
have those conversations in a very ad
hoc manner so you don't need to codify
it as much a little bit sooner you need
to codify it with the remote company and
have kind of a cold
philosophy on how you do that so we had
to do that a little bit sooner I don't
know if I would really say it's harder
it's it's definitely a trade off for
sure because like on the other side you
get lots of amazing benefits from being
remote and we've mentioned a few at the
top those are things like no commute you
can hire you know everybody anyone in
the world if you find an amazing
engineer and some small town in Ohio
they don't want to move they have a
family there or whatever then you can
hire that person and they can work with
you where is that wouldn't really be
possible if you were collocate so
there's lots of benefits that you get
and I think you there are some
trade-offs that you have to be aware of
so that you can approach it
appropriately yeah I was going to ask
and you hit on this idea that there are
some challenges I there's challenges and
everything so I was gonna ask what are
the top three challenges in managing a
distributed team you mentioned that some
of the things that companies who scale
some of the problems you may get earlier
are there a couple of others that that
come to mind as the the big rocks people
can expect to encounter if they start
working on or using distributed remote
team members yeah I would say for sure
one challenge I've seen especially for
teams and companies that maybe aren't
ready to go a hundred percent remote but
want to let's say layer in a little bit
remote and you know dip their toe in the
water so to say a big challenge around
that is when you have I would say it's
kind of it turns into kind of clicks of
like the in-office verse out of office
folks and if there's any like barriers
of trust or any ways where stuff happens
in the office that people feel left out
or there's like communication
difficulties and the mediums and
channels that naturally are in each
environment that can be particularly
challenging so one thing I would
definitely call out tips for that I
would make sure that you don't go with
the pattern of having let's say managers
who are co-located and the rest of team
who is completely remote I think that
that adds like an arbitrary division
there I would try to keep entire teams
remote if you could pull that off
I would say certainly for companies who
want to introduce this - think carefully
about
the channels they default to for
communications so let's say you're gonna
have a meeting you're gonna invite a
bunch of people somewhere cool located
somewhere remote if you just have
everyone get together in that same room
and they have that face-to-face physical
intimacy with that the people across the
the wire do not that creates this
artificial barrier I know some companies
like fog Creek would have people go into
different rooms and they would all be
co-located but remote and how they would
interact and that would help level the
playing field a little bit so that you
kind of brought to the forefront this
the medium the default medium is across
the video chat rather than you know
something happening off camera or a
common you know a comment made this way
or a conversation that happens that the
mic didn't quite catch you know like
those little things add up and aggregate
to kind of harm the the effectiveness of
having remote and co-located together so
those are some of the things I'd be
watching out for especially around
challenging and challenges and trying to
mitigate those challenges yeah you hit
onto the area I want to actually move
into next that's kind of the culture of
remote company will use the phrase
remote and distributed interchangeably
during this episode so what are the key
cultural elements for building effective
remote teams or or in this case an
entire remote company yeah it's a great
question so it's a peer we've we've
definitely thought pretty critically
about the values that we have in our
culture and we started from I mean I
think everybody's been in a company that
has the poster values it's like be
excellent
you know achieve greatness which they
feel so empty that they go we call them
poster values because they just they
just they exist on a poster only right
ours are a little more behavioral driven
and they're more let's say tuned to what
we want and behavior is inside the org
one of the first examples one of my
favorite ones it's our first value is
default to action
we're remote so we deal with time zones
we deal with people's availabilities we
definitely have a more I would say
forgiveness over permissions sort of the
culture and that's
captured in default to action where if
you're not sure what to do exactly
maybe the person you really need the
answer from is in a different time zone
and they're not available make your best
guess we would much rather you make a
decision move forward and be productive
then kind of sit back and wait for the
official word or anything like that
and that's that's a behavior that we can
opt into as an organization and a great
value is something where you could take
the opposite let's say you're in a
regulated environment defaulting to
action and making a call without all the
information especially with life and
lemons at stake probably not a great
value for your company right not not
something you want to do so for us it
really speaks to the culture we want to
create we want people unblock themselves
we want them to make best guesses we
want them to act autonomously and that
value encodes those behaviors and you
can see it playing out all the time
you'll see it in our slack room someone
will be like ask a question and they
won't get a response for like 20 minutes
and the way like I'm gonna we have
emojis that are like DT a default to
action like I'm just defaulting to
action with this someone yell at me if I
should enter it like whatever right and
at that point they're unblocked they're
moving forward they've they put a flag
in the sand of like hey if someone wants
to revisit this I'm open but I'm gonna
continue moving forward and that's a
really healthy thing to have in a
distributed remote environment because
you can't have people block because you
know the world has to spend an entire
time around for the next person to come
online so that's an example of how
adding some very you know very specific
cultural values and behaviors can really
drive how a remote organization thrives
and communicates are there any other key
cultures that you're trying to build I
really like that one I just wonder are
there a couple of others you could you
could share with us that you have found
especially with remote teams are are
really critical yeah absolutely another
of our values is default to transparency
doesn't mean everything's transparent in
fact there is a spectrum there's some
optimal position on the spectrum where
if you're too transparent and every
single thing you ever do goes into the
room and you're talking to everybody and
like just opinion it like going crazy
there that's too much right like so
there's there's this aspect of being
transparent but also like aggressively
summarizing and making sure to to pull
in the right people at the right time to
be more verbose but do it in a like
bring the noise level down there's lots
of like techniques like that that we've
encoded inside of our culture around
transparency that really help people
gather context so if you were again if
you're offline because of the time zone
difference you can pop into a room and
see some of the decisions that have been
making see some of the docs of then
opened up and some of the comments in
there this is the same for like github
and PR it's like there's probably lots
of places in your organization as well
you're already doing some of this stuff
but we try to encode it into a lot of
the day-to-day behaviors as well and for
defaults of transparency like I said
it's a spectrum there's there's places
where it might be too far right like
there's it doesn't mean everything is
transparent it means that by default you
probably want to make it transparent but
if you have a good reason not to then it
doesn't need to be transparent so
there's there's a there's a practicality
embedded in that and one thing we've
often done is like listed out a couple
examples of places and behaviors that
fall in line with these and that really
helps the team kind of internalize these
and convert sometimes abstract ideas
into specific behaviors which is always
challenging so we've we've done things
to help bridge that gap a little bit as
well you've mentioned the terms
codifying and encoding which makes me
think that somewhere these things might
be written down just maybe not on a
poster but though but I'm curious when
when someone joins a traditional company
they walk in the door they may go
through an onboarding employee
orientation process they will
immediately get a sense of what
accepted by the way their team members
talk and the environment they're in but
in this case your team members might be
in coffee shops bedrooms home offices
all over the world how do you
communicate and teach this these
cultural values to new people that's a
great question
this is something that we've been
experimenting a bit with in 2019
certainly it starts with the values
certainly it starts there and it starts
with some of what I was talking about
like trying to turn seemingly abstract
values into specific behaviors both
positive and negative so kind of we show
you and I think there's a great I think
Ben Horowitz had this like good product
manager bad product manager that kind of
inspired that like like here's a good
example of defaulting exam to action
here's a bad example we're using it as
an excuse to push something that
shouldn't have you know things like that
and we get specific that really really
helps but the place where I've been
experimenting a bit and 2019 is leaning
into our value of remote as a part of
onboarding so we used to do this thing
where we would fly folks out to the Bay
Area every not every month not every
body but the new folks on the team and
kind of do a little bit of an onboarding
week and this worked really really well
it helped us connect with all the new
folks on the team and we got to talk
through some of these values and work
together and that was really really
great but we kind of were looking at it
like is this really in alignment with
how we think about remote like we're a
remote first company shouldn't we be
able to onboard people in a remote way
and we kind of took that as a challenge
to try to build out a remote first like
you join zapier and you spend your first
three months like remote right like you
are in it and we try to really we try to
bake in some ideas around like graduated
autonomy so that first week your time is
pretty much like stacked like you're
doing all kinds of stuff you're learning
about all the different things that we
have going on you're learning about some
of the values and not just you know the
abstract but also hey here's like some
specific behavior like we're going into
that and then each and every week we're
backing off from you know booking over
booking your calendar to giving you a
little bit more time
I'm if you're an engineer now you're
you're writing a little bit of code
you're working on this you're working on
that if you're a product manager you're
starting ass back outs of stuff you're
starting to work with like the team
you're a manager you're starting to take
over one-on-ones right so we're kind of
ramping this up over time but you still
have that foundational base that
everyone had and it's starting a remote
as like the ground foundation for it so
that's something that's a little bit new
in 2019 and so far it's gone really
really well a lot of the we do a lot of
surveys inside us happier to figure out
you know how how is this how is that
very focus on different facets and in
this case onboarding and so far things
are looking pretty good so I think if
you spend the time to critically think
about what people need to know during
that onboarding phase and really embed
your cultural values and the things you
care about into that and let us shape it
at a very fundamental level then the
values kind of come out during the
onboarding and the transition phase into
like doing your role day-to-day and then
it's then it becomes just second nature
that was your introduction that's how
you live and zapier that's how is
happier meets you so it feels very
natural at that point it seems like when
you do anything that changes the culture
the practices whether it's dramatic or
even small there's an opportunity for
some people to get out of the loop I'm
imagining manager X at your company who
accidentally on board somebody the old
way because they didn't quite get the
message that there was a new way to do
things and then right they're frustrated
how do you overcome when things change
keeping the especially key people like
managers and leads who affect those
below them making sure that they're
really informed and empowered with
what's with where you're going well I
think that comes back to a little bit of
what we're talking about with
transparency we're trying to do a better
job at change management just in general
because again we're back on the spectrum
of like too transparent like if you pre
announced something that has some very
you sort of get this behavior of oh
that's changing I'm not going
I'll just pause my work on that then
until that lands right and that's a very
natural sort of behavior we want to
avoid that sort of thing but we also
don't want to hide stuff so we there's
like a there's like this delicate
balance around that around really trying
to put to the forefront hey here's the
things we're looking at and the stuff
that we want to improve and talking
about maybe some of the places that our
current process is failing or isn't in
alignment with some of our values and
some of the ways that we can improve it
and then really trying to hone in on a
rollout plan and an action plan for that
so that people know when it's coming but
they also you have having some of that
awareness that is coming you can even
call out like hey this doesn't mean that
things stop right that doesn't mean that
we're going into pause mode while we
figure this out this means we're looking
at it so that's a delicate balance I
don't I don't think we've solved it
let's say but we're definitely getting
more practice at it and communication is
a big part of that I know we have some
internal tools that we use that help
communicate these sorts of things we've
started to bacon some company level
metrics stuff that really helped guide
and frame some of these conversations so
often the question is like well why are
we why are we changing this and you can
point at some specific like well we are
trying to we're trying to drive
activation here and because the team was
structured this way or that way made it
really hard to impact that because we
were looking at you know three to
six-month roadmap rather than looking at
the iteration cadence of experiments or
something like so now we have a
framework in which to discuss those
things and that really helps give
context as to why things are changing
which we found is often if you have
curious folks they want to know why why
why are we changing this and if you can
give a really solid reasoning and secret
of events that get you there you get a
lot of trust and ability to make a
change try an experiment and lay in some
of these optimizations over time yeah
but I want to move over to the topic of
software development processes and
quality but before we do I'm really
curious lots of folks in our industry
are familiar with Conway's law and the
idea that the way we're organised
impacts the products we build and
there's a reflection there is that true
of remote teams as well yeah I think so
and we lean into this and I'll give you
a really specific example how we've
leaned into certainly remote but our
product in and of itself is an
automation tool so we should be really
big advocates and have a big passion for
automation so one of our values is
actually don't be a robot build the
robot where we dog food a ton of this
like you'll if you were to hop into a
slack room inside of zapier there up box
from running all over doing all kinds of
stuff for people and we've tried to
structure our company around the things
we want to we want to embed into the
product and the way we build a product
and that's like an example of something
that may be you know I think Conway's
law often alludes to you know the the
fundamental architecture or maybe
software or something like that but we
think of it even one layer above that
like what it what's the output of what
we're trying to build in terms of the
product and how do we big that into our
culture another big one that we've done
since the beginning and we still do that
I love doing and is actually a pretty
big hit for everyone is everybody does
support its app here so every single
week or every two weeks it depends on
what schedule you are we do what we call
is all hands support it means everyone
hops in starts helping customers and
it's amazing the kinds of stuff people
are doing with the product but it's also
amazing when they hit little bumps and
they hit little places of friction
how much empathy it gives us because if
you're working on they're working on the
code that maybe is producing a bug to
see how that bug hits people really
helps close that feedback loop or on the
positive side if you ship something that
really helps someone and then you later
see a couple weeks later someone saying
thank you that's amazing I can't believe
I'm able to do XYZ as a result of that
it really helps close the loop there but
this is this is not just for software
engineers this is everyone so all execs
do it all marketing folks do it all the
biz dev folks do you name it everyone's
doing support at some part
time and zapier so that again building
structures building a culture around
supporting the product and supporting
the customer is kind of the level at
which I think kana is wet law could
really be put to like good effect versus
just a strictly engineering sense which
is how I traditionally thought about it
let's shift over to the topic of
software development quality is it
harder to build software in a remote
environment no I don't think so in fact
I think that a remote environments a bit
more conducive to the ways that let's
say engineers work everyone's probably
super familiar with the huge success of
open-source as like a model that is
almost exclusively done with folks who
are working remotely on particular
things and I I can't think of a bigger
movement and software than that so I
feel like it's pretty natural and that's
pretty good evidence that it is but even
if you just think of how engineers work
on a day to day basis you want to
control your environment you want to
like Zone in on stuff you want to drop
distractions in an open office
environment or layout or if you have to
commute somewhere it eats up into that
attention that you have so we've
definitely noticed that engineers in
particular really enjoy working remote
you can be in a quiet room you can
control the heat you don't have to
listen to someone playing music that's
distracting to you you don't have to
listen to sales calls happening a
cubicle over or whatever that I think is
really really powerful and all the tools
for building software this is all it's
all digital artifacts right like you're
creating code you're uploading it to
github or gitlab you're reviewing it
there you're living in the digital realm
you're living over the web and over the
internet already so kind of making that
the base foundational place where work
happens is not a stretch I don't feel
like I don't feel like that's that's
that crazy I know a lot of times
certainly folks who have maybe seen
remote not work well in a co-located mix
environment or maybe haven't done it
before kind of have this gut reaction of
like how could that possibly work if you
can't see someone you know in their seat
right and I
I just think that's a fundamentally
flawed way to look at how people are
productive whereas like you can you can
see was somewhat like if someone has a
PR open and the code is doing what it
needs to do and it's getting reviewed
the way it needs to do and it's getting
shipped in a remote environment it just
there's no difference right the factors
you get to emphasize a lot of the
strengths there so to us we feel like
software development in particular is
something that is bolstered in a great
way by which agile ceremonies do you use
and how have you altered them to be
remote first friendly yeah so we're not
really dictatorial on like agile or
scrum or any of the processes we tend to
encourage teams find a pattern that
works well for them and we try to have
the interfaces out to the rest of the or
be a little bit clearer so things like
dates that you're gonna ship something
especially if another team has something
that they need they have a reliance on
you that's something you'll need to
export in a consistent way but how you
get the work done that's more of a team
decision classic you know differences a
product team that has a very defined
like roadmap versus a infrastructure
team that is very much dealing with
things that are popping up as team needs
this and use that and that's a very
scrum verse Kanban style like divide
whichever one works is great but at the
end of the day we still need to be able
to communicate and export some of those
those common interfaces so we try to pay
attention to that more so than the
particulars of how work gets done that
said we do like to have some consistency
so if you just want to pop something off
the shelf and be like I was gonna do
this and you just want to go with that
fine like that works really real well
and you can just kind of lean into that
and you get some nice benefits if you
have engineers that swap between teams
or are gonna hop in and help you out
with this or that it'll feel very
natural and that's good so we do see
some value around consistency but we
don't enforce consistency for
consistency sake if that makes sense
yeah are there some favorite ceremonies
do people do stand-ups do you do ma
synchronously do you use retrospectives
you do estimation
I'm just curious what what have you
found that's actually working that many
teams or maybe your some of your best
teams have leveraged yeah so we
definitely do
grooming meetings where we try to get
everybody together and this kind of
comes back to some of the time zone
stuff we try to make sure that there's
some overlap so those those
conversations can't happen let's say the
other place that I would say that we
have a consistency is the medium in
which you communicate needs to be on the
more asynchronous side I would say slack
is not often the best place for that
because by the time you wake up it's you
know it's slid on there's a million
conference you got to catch up it's it's
unrealistic to think that everybody can
stay on top of every message that comes
through slack so that's not the place to
default to conversation
well maybe not conversations but
certainly decisions being made or kind
of like where artifacts should live
because they're not discoverable it's an
okay place to have like a one-on-one
conversation of trying to like get down
to a decision but it needs to be pushed
into a tool like JIRA or something like
that
so we've often had you know the the
mechanism of where communication our
sorry decisions get made push those into
tools that are more asynchronous and
more evergreen esque
it's like a big aspect of what we do but
overall I think remote gives you the
flexibility to try and like plate with a
couple of these things we don't have
rules around daily stand-ups for example
if teams find that really useful that's
great I know a lot of teams do slack
handoffs where at the end of the day
they'll do a handoff and they'll tag it
is such and then they'll just summarize
some of the stuff they did that day some
of the stuff they need for the next day
and that's a way for them to communicate
where they're at with each other
so those are some things that have kind
of caught on and spread between teams
but again they're not enforced in any
way in traditional companies one of the
challenges that I see is when teams need
to make technical decisions together
sometimes it's the most opinionated
person the hype most highly paid person
the person who's the architect there's
lots of different dynamics around team
decision making is there a particular
best practice you've found for how how
your team's make
technical decisions so the best way is
that the technical decisions are how
technical decisions get made right yeah
yeah exactly so we try to have as much
of a bottoms-up approach to some of
these decisions as we can we find that
makes people more autonomous it helps
them make the decisions that are okay or
makes sense for them locally we have
leaned into using more frameworks around
helping people I want to say like the
Dacey models things like that that help
people kind of dictate where the bounds
are of some of these decisions and if
it's in a lot of cases it might be an
individual engineer you could be the
driver the approver the contributor and
the informed parties of a particular
decision you're making so you can just
like go nuts on that and you don't have
to pull in a bunch of people but if
you're gonna cross boundaries into
another team now you're starting to pull
in certainly has to be informed that
this is changing but you might want them
to contribute as well like you start to
pull in other people and like raise the
scope of these sorts of things and we
have people inside the orb we're doing a
little bit better job here 2019 that can
help you help you think through some of
that so instead of them automatically
being the approver or whoever like maybe
that an architect in that case they
might actually come in and be like
actually you know you can just make this
call and that might be the sort of
support that they give you just to kind
of give you a second second pair of eyes
so to say on a decision you might make
so this is something that we're learning
a lot more about in 2019 then we have in
the past and so far it's been going it's
goin pretty well kind of like providing
those bounds and some examples I think
also really helped play into that
because this is something that we've as
you get bigger it becomes a bigger issue
when you're smaller everyone kind of
knows what's going on so you kind of get
away with it but there is a transition
when you you know passed a dozen or so
people working on a single area and the
code base like it starts to really push
you to do this one of the challenges
I've seen engineering teams have is
collaborating and working effectively
with the product teams this is in
co-located startups all kinds of
different companies it seems like
sometimes engineering and product aren't
communicate
well that there can be some challenges
do you find any particular challenges
that the engineering teams have working
with product teams and remote
environments no I I don't think there is
particular ones that are unique to
remote this is something that we've
we're trying to improve upon in again
this year is a big focus is trying to
get we kind of call it the like the trio
or a trifecta or Triforce it depends on
who's talking about it where engineering
product and design or we want it we want
it to feel like when you enter one of
those grooming meetings or whatever
you're not really sure who's the product
person who's an engineer who's the
design because everyone's has like a
similar level of understanding and stake
and pushing on stuff and that is
something that we're certainly like
early in the stages of rolling out is
happier but it's something that is
certainly aspirational for us and you
know some of the some of the things that
we've certainly seen in the past we've
had a lot more product driven around
kind of roadmaps
engineering around the co.design around
the CSS of the markup and those have
kind of they're not silos it's not the
right word for it but certainly the area
of focus but kind of pulling them all
together and kind of making sure that
people care about across the line so
designers can you know make an argument
for reducing some tech debt over here
and really push for that where as an
engineer I might look at some of the
roadmap stuff and make an argument for
pulling out some refactoring and saying
actually there's a is a simpler way we
can test this and here's how it might
look like those kinds of interesting
advocates are things that we're trying
to make room for sort of in the
organization so this is stuff I think
we're early in the process at
discovering so it's something that maybe
in another year if I came back on I
might have a little more insight into
well that'd be great let's switch over
to managing these teams are there
special challenges your managers face
when managing remote teams it's a good
question like I said I think humans are
humans in both remote and co-located
environments so a lot of the stuff that
you would deal with in a
located environment exists in remote in
a few cases you might see the
elimination of a few things it's really
funny there is a there's a great podcast
out there for managers called
miniature toolkit I believe and great
podcast has a ton of really good stuff
and they'll just walk you if they have a
bunch episodes they'll just kind of walk
you through a bunch of scenarios and
just give you some context on how other
people deal with this and some of the
interesting ones they have on there is
someone who maybe has a body odor issue
or something of that sort right so those
are things you can very comfortably be
like okay I'm not gonna have to deal
with that so that's I think something
that you can look forward to is that
it's that's not a part of the awkward
conversations you have to have but when
it comes to career growth when it comes
to working with teammates being active
on a team those sorts of things there's
not a huge difference in what you need
to do as a manager there we lean into a
weekly one-on-ones we make sure that
that happens every single week for every
direct report we make sure that
everybody has kind of that team that
they're focused on that there's clarity
about who you're working with and who
like your first team is things like that
are things that again aren't unique to
remote but are you know top of mind for
us so I'm struggling to think of
something that's like really uniquely
remote if anything that might be the
emphasis on written communication and
being clear you know for me I know like
I'll I'll start writing out a comment on
let's say github and I'll find myself
revising it three or four times before I
post it because I want the I want the
particulars of the point to be made
clearly and concisely so um I'll be very
particular about how I communicate in a
text form and I think that sort of
behavior is stuff that makes any one
side of remote org more effective and
those might be the places where you
would see a disproportionate amount of
time being spent by a manager and a
remote org versus someone in a
co-located org but overall I think the
basics are still there is not going to
be a massive Delta
between one of the other is there an
equivalent to the management practice of
walking around and listening which is
common when you can walk around the
cubicle farms and just listen for
problems yeah there definitely is some
of this is like serendipitous where you
try to create these sorts of
opportunities and some is more I would
say defined what are the ones that we
have that kind of combines both is we
use a tool called I think it's called
donut where we do pair buddies every
single week it randomly pairs you with
it used to be one other person but I
think it's groups of three three people
and it says hey you should meet this
week and you might meet with the support
person and an exec and that might be
your your group for that week you get on
you just chat about various things that
are happening and that gives you a
little bit of that kind of walking
around the office sort of the feel we
ought we really encourage folks to get
good at raising the bandwidth is
something that we often say around
conversations that happen in rooms so a
classic example here would be your
chatting in a slack room you're talking
about something and you see yourself
going back and forth and maybe that may
be a thread and slack has gone to like
30 replies back and forth like that
might be a signal that you should raise
the bandwidth and you can start pulling
in people for sort of ad hoc meetings
over let's say a zoom call and that will
let you go a little bit deeper have a
higher bandwidth situation and then once
you get to a consensus or a decision or
move something to move forward on you
can close down the call and summarize
back in that thread and that kind of
gives you the opportunity to pull people
in you may be not may not be discussing
some of those finer points with all the
time that would have traditionally
stayed on slack or would have
traditionally stayed in some written
medium get them onto a call and like
dive into something so that stuff that
you'll see inside of that peer as well
that really helps but I mean overall
like we we truly we really try to build
ways for asynchronous things like that
to happen there is we have a lot of
tools literally call it async where
people can post their updates it's kind
of a mix of let's say reddit meets
Twitter meets WordPress so you can see
the kinds of
things that are trending inside the
company which give you a little bit of
insight into other stuff that's
happening in a kind of structured way
but also kind of serendipitous way that
gets you a bit of that vibe of like oh
this person was working on this cool
thing and I overheard it I got to dive
into it and learn more about some of the
problems that you get a little bit of
that as well because we encourage people
to post about some of the challenges
they had that week some of the learnings
they had that reek we reflect on that
and it's a great way for people to get a
bit of an insight into that you know
what most other companies I've worked at
we we tried to adopt wiki's or we tried
to adopt some written kinds of
communication we use slack and things
like that it seems like especially when
it comes to this tool you mentioned
async well well I don't know exactly
what that is it seems like in my
experience about 20% of the people
generate 80% of the content do you find
the same thing or with remote teams is
it really that everyone is fully bought
in and if not how do you encourage how
do you encourage the the folks who don't
are aren't as active to participate it's
a great question and it depends on who
you need to be your audience for a lot
of these things and in some cases it
might be okay to have a little bit of
like 80% of the rereads or the are
co-located and 20% of the posts that
might be ok it really depends on what
the distribution is so for us a lot of
these posts are really intended for your
first team so that might mean that a
really successful async post was read by
20 people right versus you know
something that the whole company read
right the audience kind of matters there
and we try to remind people of that and
we've made some changes like over time I
think we've we've hit in like some
recounts and view counts and rescinded
like we used to have more things like
percent of companies that read this and
that kind of gave the wrong signal for
those sorts of things that's not that's
wasn't the intentionality so a lot of
these things are really kind of about
setting expectations for what is
necessary for these sorts of different
modes of communication
certainly for async we do these weekly
updates and those are for
everyone to reflect on challenges
they've had things they're excited about
stuff they're working on and those are
really for your team and sometimes for
folks outside of it to get insight into
what's going on when you kind of look at
it that way as like the intent for that
I think it works pretty well we we try
to have everybody post regularly on that
that's like kind of foundation it's just
like hey everybody should be doing like
a weekly update when it comes more to
how many people read it we try to keep
people you know we try to keep
expectations in line so people can feel
like oh this was a successful post even
if only maybe a dozen people but a dozen
of the right people read it and that's
what matters what things should managers
look out for it to indicate that
somebody's struggling that's a great
question
I would say it's easy in a remote
environment to get very quiet and be
very heads down so if you haven't heard
from someone or seen what they've been
producing that's usually a pretty good
signal it doesn't mean you necessarily
need to and this is not the same as like
micromanaging this is just like checking
up me like hey what's going on here that
I think is often like an early sign of
something this is often one of the first
bits of advice I certainly give
engineers in remote environments is
you're there's a tendency for everyone
certainly to feel what to be a peer have
the appearance of like oh I got things
under control whereas like questions or
Road that like if you're in a slack room
asking a million questions the feeling
that they put on themselves is often
like oh I'm being a being a pastor I'm
I'm signaling that I don't know what's
going on or something like that and I
found this is particularly pernicious
for engineers this is not a good
behavior to have in a remote environment
and especially for someone who's new in
an organization so I kind of like to set
an expectation of if you're not asking
you know a half dozen to a dozen
questions every day as a new engineer
like that's probably a signal that
you're going a little too Rambo or heads
down or hero mode or whatever you want
to call it where you're trying to live
up to them some expectation that is not
real so that's something that I often
point out and that
uses signals like how active are they in
the room that they're supposed to be
active in how many questions are they
asking those sorts of things and those
can be really really helpful so those
are stuff that I would be like looking
at for an engineer certainly is how
active are they especially in the early
days because you're trying to set trying
to set those how would you say those
those behaviors and those traditions for
how that person is gonna operate if it
starts off that way where it's very
quiet it tends to continue that and
that's not often an optimal way to work
I want to move to a question that's
generally a pretty hard situation for
managers and that's when people aren't
performing well right and we have to
take the next step what kinds of steps
does your company take or what kind of
steps do you recommend remote companies
take to help people get back on track or
to eventually fire them yeah always
difficult right and I would go back to
what we were saying before there's
there's not any like secret sauce for
remote that doesn't exist in probably a
co-located environment the core Maxim we
have around performance can be probably
summed up with no surprises right where
we want to be very fast on feedback we
want to be very clear on feedback and if
if you have a hard conversation let's
say with an engineer like hey this
performance is not great we need to go
to we need to escalate this to the next
level and whether that's like a
performance improvement plan or whatever
is something more formalized that that
engineers response will be like I kind
of kind of thought that this this was
coming right if that's the if that's the
feeling that each of those like points
of escalation have then you're not
surprising the person and that's a good
sign so for us it's all about fast
feedback it's all about no surprises
it's all about clarity and having those
kind of tough conversations early and
soon and I don't think that again I
don't think that's like a uniquely
remote phenomena there are I mean there
might be some like let's just say
strategy things or tactic things on how
you discuss or broach these in a maybe
not face-to-face your on a video call or
something like that but we found that
just being very
direct providing notes and summaries and
written kind of like recaps of what you
talked about and having some of that I
would say like breadcrumbs for that
engineer to be like reflecting on and
knowing where like where is the bar
where am i falling short is really
important maybe more so in a remote
environment although I would argue you
should be doing that regardless but
those are some of the things that we're
certainly thinking of when we think of
remote performance management let's say
a difficult topic for sure let's move
over to collaboration a few times you've
mentioned the idea of asynchronous
behaviors would you say that your
company is a synchronous remote company
or an asynchronous remote company I
would say we strive to be asynchronous
as much as possible there are some
necessarily synchronous portions of work
we do those I think get captured in
things like grooming meetings right
where you try to get everyone together
and discuss the plan and like break down
some of the work and get estimates
figured out those are ace those are
might be able to be done asynchronously
but we found that they work pretty well
in a synchronous manner there are it
seems like there's always some aspect
that needs to be done in a synchronous
manner so having that overlap let's say
for a team you know an hour or two and
their time zone distribution is really
really important because that
synchronous stuff is always kind of
there but as much of it that we can push
to asynchronous as possible we try to do
that you'll see things like
retrospectives we'll try to get we'll
try to do a lot of the prep in an
asynchronous manner and then get
everybody on a call and recap and
debrief on it in a secretive manner and
then we'll summarize and share an
asynchronous manner right so we tried to
like have a bit of a hybrid around some
of these things and try to use them as
best they can so I I would I would
definitely say we strive to be as much
asynchronous as possible uh-huh but if
there is some synchronous components we
recognize that and we try to try to
minimize them but we certainly try to
put them all together so that we can
optimize our time best as possible has
generally been our approach I think
we're getting better over the years as
well do you keep common work
King hours it sounds like there's some
amount of that and doesn't matter where
you live to you if you can keep those
common working hours it seems like there
might be a difference between someone's
sort of default timezone maybe is is
Western European but they're they're
really willing their a night owl so
they're willing to stay up and be on US
time do you care about that we care
about it to the degree that you're
consistent and predictable and that
doesn't mean always like sometimes
you're like hey I have to go do XYZ
therefore I'm kind of shift my day no
problem as long as you're kind of
communicating that with your team that
is not a that is not an issue grossly
inconsistent scheduling can be a source
of like friction for team because if
they if they assume that you're gonna be
available at this time or that time and
you're not then that can be that can
just throw a wrench in things so if
that's like a consistent theme that can
be a problem
we don't have core hours in the sense
that everybody has to work these hours
or anything like that that's that's
certainly that's not compatible with
like a fully distributed remote
environment I don't believe and in some
places you can really take advantage of
that time zone diversity a great example
is sre or infrastructure teams when you
have to carry the pager uh-huh it's much
nicer to carry them during working hours
right you don't want to wake up at 3:00
a.m. to servers blowing up so there are
some cases where you can actually use
time zones to your advantage and have
that kind of distributed portion of the
workforce take advantage of that so we
do try to be strategic about like time
zones and working hours but again we're
not we try not to be dictatorial about
it we ask for consistency and
predictability and working hours above a
lot of everything else let me paint this
scenario about collaboration and
communication imagine you've got a
developer who's got a great idea maybe
the current coding style doesn't work
for them or they've they've stumbled
upon something then and they propose a
refinement they have an idea for a
refinement they figure someone else must
be having this problem too how does an
idea that starts with one developer
which probably happens every day go
through a process that
impacts the entire company especially
when everyone's remote and you can't
just get that person to stand up and
yell Eureka let's do it this way yeah
it's a great question and something we
are working on still so don't take
anything I say here is being the
solution certainly for us I haven't
found it to be true that we fake figured
it out I think it comes back to a little
bit of what we're talking about with the
desi stuff how much of that can be
something you can just decide to do does
that break is it kind of additive or
does it fundamentally subvert something
we're doing because that can give you
the ability to try it out on your team
or maybe just for yourself and that's a
great way to get started and that's
alignment with some of our values around
default to action if it's something
where you're like I think we should move
all of our data to you know a different
database like all right that's probably
not something you as a team can like do
that doesn't mean we should have discuss
it but that just means that hey maybe
get an architect involved to kind of
figure out how the conversation and who
should be involved and kind of scope
that out we have mechanisms by which
whenever something escapes a team let's
say as soon as it's cross team we
modeled this thing after Python the
Python community had peps Python and
improvement or pivot is it Python
improvement process I can't remember
what it was but anyways if you google it
you'll probably find it Google will
correct you but we we model that to that
and we call them Zepps
it's a pure enhancement proposals what
we call them and that would be something
where you can formulate that you can
create a readme to mark now doc that
lives in a github so you can see all the
changes over time its first and
controlled you can tag people can have a
code review effectively as a part of
that and that's really for when the
contributors of let's say a desi model
I'm gonna go back to that again cross
teams or really impact lots of people
and that has escalated outside of
something that you your team can decide
on your own and we try to like scope
those decisions down as much as we can
because we'd rather like let's say you
want to change the way imports are done
let's say on the Python back inside so
that there's a little more isolate
for apps and for modules well that's
something you might be able to try in
your team and create like a linting rule
that only applies to the module that
you're really working on and start there
try it out for a couple weeks see how it
goes then escalate it up and hey hey
here's something we've been doing with
this team what does everyone else think
about it and at that point it feels more
natural because you have a little bit of
evidence that it can work or that it's
useful you have certainly a working
prototype and you probably have a lot
more insight into what it can help with
and what it can't help with and that is
a much more fertile place to be starting
from than strictly I got an idea Eureka
right now everybody like way in right so
this is kind of defaulting in action and
like raising or increasing like the
scope of which that thing might impact
is like a really natural way for stuff
to happen that doesn't work for every
single situation that you want to try
but it's a good place to start and
generally it makes a little bit easier
on everyone involved to kind of do it in
that graduated manner I really like that
it also seems respectful of the fact
that these good ideas do come from
everywhere and kind of allows anyone who
wants to go through the work to write up
one of these EPS at least that's my
guess it gives them an outlet rather
than just complaining about something
100% yeah yeah and it doesn't it doesn't
always mean that your sap is gonna get
like every again like the the right you
want the right people to look at it it
may not mean that everyone's gonna weigh
in or it might it might die on the vine
let's say right and that's okay like
we'd rather have ideas put out there
without fear of certainly kind of this
expectation that it has to go live or it
has to happen but it said hey it's a
discussion a lot of times stuff will pop
up and we'll say hey we want to change
the way deployments are done and we'll
talk about it and we can't get to really
a great consensus point but it'll
illuminate a couple very specific things
in the deployment process maybe the way
we do migrations which is a little bit
friction inducing and so we'll say okay
let's close this up because this is
maybe trying to bite off too much let's
roll these pieces of the conversation
into another one and talk about that
specific answer these things sprout off
and create new
positions so it's always as a continuum
of ideas and ways that we can be better
even though that that one particular
thing may not have been what we rolled
out or what we landed on or even got
even remotely close to where we all
agreed on it but instead like we can
still pick and pull out little good bits
and remix those throughout the org so
that we found that that to be a pretty
useful pattern it's something we haven't
perfected yet
but I think is probably on the
directionally correct let's say
everybody likes to talk about tools what
are the tools that remote teams just
live and die by these days well I would
say things like SAP you're really useful
if you're working often online with SAS
products SAS software where all your
work lives having a tool to automate
some of your life I mean oh you know for
me like right now my slack status says
that I'm on a podcast right that's his
app that's set up on my Google Calendar
that automatically updates my status and
slack it's an aggregate of like your org
having these behaviors and these
automated things happening for you which
is really really valuable so I would say
things like that try to automate as much
of your life as you can and then try to
figure out the the places you want to
communicate for us the you know first
layer is probably slack it's where a lot
of synchronous communication happens
it's where most stuff defaults to we
have some specialized tools I mentioned
that async
we built that ourselves it's like I said
it's kind of read it meets Twitter meets
WordPress where it's an internal thing
that's where a lot of conversations end
up and a lot of like retrospectives and
changelogs and friday updates and like
that goes in there and that's a great
place to put stuff but we also have a
lot of the other tooling that you're
probably really familiar with where work
happens we have the JIRA's and the
github x' and those sorts of things
where a lot of work happens we use tools
like Sigma for the design side of things
we have lots of these like special
best-in-class best and buried tools for
all those particular pieces so it's not
really dissimilar to what enough again
other companies are already doing like
how a lot of their work exists I mean I
bet you most co-located
these are writing code and pushing it to
github or get lap right we do the same
thing so a lot of the stuff and a lot of
the patterns that exist there are
directly transferable to sort of the
remote environment you just might lean
on it a bit more it might need to you
know encode some of the behaviors a
little more specifically over time
rather than kind of being a more
laissez-faire about them I don't think I
heard you say email this is something
co-located teams use a lot of we do not
use any email almost I I'm trying to
think of the last email I sent to
someone inside of zapier that was
literally just to then I don't know if
I'm trying to literally think of an
example in the history of zapier the
only times we ever do email is certainly
external so like when we were
coordinating this call of course like
you got to do email like that makes
sense that is probably the only place we
use email the only place we use email
internally is maybe forwarding like hey
I got this email from a partner
forwarded on can you take care of this
kind of a thing
maybe but like 99.9% of our
communication happens in slack
especially inside of the organization
yeah I don't think we do email is not a
thing that internal comms at all let's
round out this conversation with looking
back a little bit knowing what you know
now is you guys have evolved and you've
built this remote company if you were
gonna start over what would you do
differently always a interesting
question because I think we're just so
fortunate like SAP here is such a cool
product it's something that we're all
like really excited about that I I would
hesitate to change much if it would
change the outcome right like cuz like
we're just really lucky to have a
product that resonates with as many
people as it does and I have such a
great team that I would be really
careful messing with that you know some
of the stuff that we did in the early
days like leaning into remote I uh I
really think was the right call some of
the stuff that I wish we probably would
have done better I don't know if I'd
call it I don't know if I would say that
it's unique to remote I would say some
of the stuff that I look back on and I
wish we maybe would have put in place
sooner might have been better career
progression level
like we stayed like we had titling was
like pretty like pretty flat titling in
the sense even though we did we did have
hierarchy we had managers and things
like that we believed in that of course
but in terms of titling and growth like
that was it was pretty flat and I think
that makes it difficult more difficult
to have those conversations of growing
folks so that might be something I would
have done a little bit sooner in terms
of the product you know I think we've
been pretty fortunate that the product
itself has we've never really vivid it
like I know that's like a thing that
like startups do right like I we pivoted
we've always been automation like we've
always done that we've been additive so
in the early days it was just trigger to
an action right and now we do many steps
right so you can do as many actions as
you want so we've been always additive
in the product and then the architecture
has always followed suit as a part of
that so there's never been any really
massive pivots or like revelations we're
like oh we should have done that in the
beginning so I would say we've been very
fortunate that the product in the
company and the folks we've hired have
really been aligned going in the right
direction Brian thank you so much for
joining us today on software engineering
radio if people want to find out more
about you or zapier where can they find
you yeah you can find does a pure com
we have we have a we're hiring a bunch
so you can get a good insight into the
stuff that we're doing there where I am
from managers certainly Python devs
JavaScript devs you've been trying to
fill out more of our something new for
us in 2019 is director level folks as
well so we're adding like new layers of
management and side of zaptor which is
really exciting so there's a lot of that
so that might be a good way for folks to
engage with SAP here try out the product
we have free sort of portion to it I
know folks here might be of the more
engineering persuasion we let you write
Zack JavaScript and Python steps inside
your workflow so you can do some really
cool stuff you can have action or
triggers that happen off the slack
messages or whatever and then run a
little Python
to go do this or that I do a lot of that
myself so that might be ways for folks
to kind of mess around and kind of
inject some of this stuff into their
into their lives but of course the folks
have any questions for me like all of
our emails are on
website publicly so I'm always happy to
field questions as you can tell I'm kind
of nervous about a lot of this stuff so
I'll talk to people zeros off on it so
thank you for your time
of course thank you markets public
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website @ SC - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC radio
slack calm you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of SU radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening